absolutely love these pillows hey what's
up guys my name is the Cho and welcome
back to my C++ series So today we're
back on the couch you guys seem to dig
that didn't have much time to go
anywhere exciting for this video however
the content is going to make up for that
because today we're going to be learning
all about how to use Visual Studio to
debug our code now in planning this
series unfortunately I have the
difficult decision of trying to decide
which video goes where in what order and
all that stuff a lot of these videos
kind of depend on each other so if you
see me mention things in certain videos
that I haven't mentioned in previous
videos it doesn't mean that I've kind of
glossed over the topic it just means
that this probably going to come later
that being said though debugging is just
such an important part of programming
and not just programming but of learning
because if you know how to debug your
code you're actually going to understand
how the program works and how the
computer actually runs your code so I
thought I'd covered debugging pretty
early on in this series because I'm
actually going to use a lot of what we
cover today to explain how the rest of
the language and how computer programs
work in general in this video
specifically like all of my C++ videos
I'm going to be using visual studio
however these Concepts apply to pretty
much any IDE out there most idees will
support exactly what I'm going to show
here today just might be in a different
place but basically we're going to be
covering two important features or three
is it three I don't even know how many
we can probably break this thing into
two parts break points see that joke
earlier was funny cuz break points is is
a big part of debugging and looking at
memory so break points and reading
memory those are kind of the two big
parts of debugging and of course you
will be using them together so in other
words you'll set break points in order
to read memory so what's the point of
debugging what do I mean when I say
let's debug our code the word debug
means to debug right so to remove bugs
from our code in order to remove a bug
from our code we have to diagnose what's
wrong with our program and that part can
actually be pretty tricky even if you're
well experienced in the language at the
end of the day you have to remember that
the computer is always right and by
always I mean like 99% of the time it's
very unlikely that you did something
correctly and then the computer just
didn't work as expected it's usually
it's usually you who made the mistake
and coming to realize that is something
that is very important for programmers
you will soon learn that the computer is
pretty much always right so really this
is all about figuring out your mistake
what did I do wrong what did I do to
deserve this so break points reading
memory let's take a look so here I have
a pretty simple Visual Studio project
I've just got my main file here which
calls log this is the log. CPP and log.
that we made in the previous video in
the video about C++ header files what
we're going to do first of all is we're
going to set a breakpoint and then we're
going to step through the execution of
our program so what are break points so
a breako is a point in our program at
which the debugger will break and the
word break here just means pause so what
will happen is we can basically set a
break point on any line of code in our
program and when when the execution hits
that line it will pause it will suspend
that execution thread or in our case the
entire program and let us take a look at
the state of this program and by state
I'm really referring to memory we can
pause our program and just take a look
at what is going on in its memory
remember the memory of a running program
is pretty much all it's got It's what
every variable is set to it's what
function will be called Next everything
when you when you break it down memory
is all all that there is really so being
able to view Memory is incredibly useful
in diagnosing what the issue is with
your program because by viewing the
memory you can see what every variable
is set to and be like hey this variable
shouldn't be set to this value
something's obviously wrong you can also
step through the execution of your
program line by line so I can put a
breakpoint on line five and then just
just hit a button and the program will
advance just one line of code further
into line six you can also step into
functions to see where they'll take you
there's just there's so much you can do
with break points it's amazing and it's
incredibly useful and if you're
programming without this then I don't
even know what you're doing so back to
visual studio in order to set a
breakpoint in Visual Studio you can
either just hit F9 and it will set a
breakpoint on that current lineup code
or you can can click on this sidebar
anywhere on the sidebar here just click
once and you'll set a breakpoint
obviously if you do something like set a
breakpoint on line three that's not
really going to work because there's
nothing on line 3 that's ever going to
get executed so make sure you set a
breako on code that actually will be
executed on lines that will actually be
hit so line six of course will be hit
because that's the first line of code in
our program and then all you have to do
is run your code through the debugger
one tip is to make sure that you're in
debug mode because if you're in release
mode the compiler will actually change
the the way that your code looks and
your break points might not ever get hit
because your program has been rearranged
we'll talk more in depth about what
release mode actually does and all that
stuff later but the gist is if you're
debugging just make sure you're in debug
mode if we then hit the local Windows
debugger which ensures that we're
actually running with the debugger
attached our program will run and you
can see that the focus from our program
is actually stolen back to visual studio
and we change into this kind of
different alternate layout along with a
big yellow arrow on on that breakpoint
indicating that that is currently where
the instruction pointer is at in our
program the main areas to look at here
are basically this continue button which
will continue executing our program like
normal and then we have a bunch of
buttons over here that let us step into
step over or step out now these three
buttons are going to control exactly
what happens next in our program so step
into is going to step into the current
function that is on this line of code if
there is a function so in this case if I
hit step into onto log we would actually
step into the log function so that we
could see what it does step over is
going to step over to the next line of
code in this current function and step
out is actually going to step out of
this current function and take us back
to whatever called this function which
in this case since this is the main
function will be the C standard Library
you can also use f11 to step into F10 to
step over or shift f11 to step out so
let's step into this log function and
see what happens I'm going to hit f11
okay check this out so we step into this
function where at the very beginning of
the stack frame we haven't actually
begun executing any code here we're just
setting up the function stack frame we
can hover our Mouse over this message
variable and check this out it tells us
that it's set to hello world so that's
the second part of debugging right we're
reading memory now how cool is this if I
hit F10 it's going to bring us up to
this line of code now the fact that the
yellow arrow is on this line of code
means that it actually hasn't executed
this line of code yet it's just it's on
there it's about to as soon as we hit a
button like F10 or shift f11 to get out
of the function or F5 which will
continue our program as soon as we hit
one of those it's going to execute that
line of code and possibly more but the
yellow arrow means that it is on that
line of code it hasn't actually executed
that line of code yet so if I bring up
my program right now you can see that
that hello world message has not been
printed but check this out if I hit F10
and then check back look at that we've
printed hello world because we've called
that s CDC out function and it actually
has printed that text to the console
we've executed that function so by
setting break points and by stepping
through our program we can literally run
our entire program line by line which of
course is really cool and really useful
when you're trying to figure out what
you've done wrong anyway back here if we
keep hitting F10 you'll see that we'll
eventually get back to our main function
F10 again will bring us to the next line
of code in our main function and this
will kind of keep going if I hit F5 it's
going to continue running our program as
usual and I can just hit enter to close
my program as if it was just running
normally all right so pretty cool stuff
and even though this might look really
simple this is actually really all there
is to it I mean I've shown you guys
pretty much everything I'll show you
some more examples so that you really
get it but that's kind of the gist of it
so let's go ahead and make some more
variables to make things interesting I'm
going to make an integer called a set it
equal to 8 I'm going to do A++ which
will increment a by one so in other
words it will set a to be 9 I'm going to
create a C string here by just typing in
Conch string
equals hello I'm going to write a very
basic for Loop here that's going to
iterate through this string and print
each character out on a separate line
and then I'll leave in my log Holo world
for good measure so if I run my program
with no break points at all just to see
what even happens you'll see that we get
basically something like this where we
have hello and then hello world all
right now let's step through this line
by line so I'm going to set a breakpoint
at the very top here on int a and just
hit F5 all right all right cool let's
take a look what a is what why is it 858
million well remember that yellow arrow
doesn't mean that we've actually run
this code we're actually just about to
run it but we haven't actually executed
line six the line that actually creates
and sets that a variable so what the
debugger is currently showing us is what
the memory where a would be is showing
right now and since we haven't actually
set that variable to anything yet it's
just uninitialized memory which means
that this value is just showing us
whatever that memory actually contains
this would be a fantastic time to bring
up these three important windows that we
have here autos locals and watch utos
and locals will basically just try and
show you local variables or variables
that it thinks might be important to you
watch on the other hand lets us actually
monitor variables so what I can do is I
can type in a which is the name of the
variable and hit enter and you can see
that it's showing me the value of a if I
also want to viiew what string is I can
also put that in and it's going to show
show me what string is now of course we
haven't initialized this memory yet so
it's currently it's completely useless
it's just garbage but as we step through
our program these values will update to
show what's actually in the memory
speaking of memory there's actually a
view that we can use to view the entire
memory of our program now of course it's
called the memory view so if we go debug
Windows memory and memory one we're
going to be graded by this weird looking
panel here that's going to show all of
the memory of our program so on the very
left we see the memory addresses in the
middle we see the actual data the actual
values represented in heximal format and
on the right we see the asky
interpretation of those numbers if you
want to locate where this a variable
actually is stored in the memory of your
program you need to know its memory
address and to do that we can simply
type in Ampersand and a so the Ampersand
in front of a variable name will
actually get that variable's memory
address if we hit enter we're going to
be taken to the memory address of that a
variable which in this case is a whole
bunch of C's so that number that CC
number is actually a heximal value if
you want to see what that is in decimal
you can bring up a calculator if we
switch to the programmer view we can
type in the heximal value if I just
click on hexadecimal here type in CC and
you can see what that value is in
decimal it's 204 so 204 CC why is it
said to that isn't that memory just
supposed to be random a whole bunch of
CC's seems kind of specific now that's
the cool thing about debug mode and also
why debug mode slows down our program
it's because the compiler will actually
make our program do certain things
certain extra things that's going to
make our lives easier when it comes to
debugging so for example the fact that
this memory is a whole bunch of CC's
means that it is uninitialized stack
memory so what's actually happened is
the compiler knows that we're making
we're trying to make a variable but we
haven't initialized it yet so what is
going to do is actually fill that memory
with CC so that if we're debugging our
code and something goes wrong we can
look at the memory we we can see that
it's set to CC and we can be like oh of
course I never initialize that variable
that's why this is going all wrong now
by doing extra things like that like
setting our memory to CC before we
initialize it obviously our program is
doing extra things that are going to
slow it down so we don't want to be
doing that in release mode when we
actually release our program when we
ship our game we don't want to be doing
all that but when it comes to debugging
is so useful so if I come over here and
I hit F10 a lot of things are going to
happen one other thing you you can do
actually in this watch window is right
click and select hexadecimal display and
so now you can see that the value of a
actually is a whole bunch of C's which
of course means that a is currently
uninitialized stack memory let's go back
to our non-hex aimal display and let's
hit F10 and a number of cool things are
going to happen so namely in this watch
window our value has changed to eight
it's also red which indicates that it's
changed since the last break point our
instruction Point has moved down which
is showing that it's now about about
about to execute this line of code
hasn't done it yet no no no not yet but
it's about to and then if we look in our
memory view you can also see that these
four bytes of memory have been set to
eight by the way I should probably
mention that every two digits here is
equal to one by that's also why we're
viewing this in hexadecimal because if
we do that every two heximal digits are
always going to align to be one bite of
memory so we can tell just by looking at
this that these eight heximal digits are
four bytes of memory and you can see
that it's been set to8 so that's what
we're doing that's all we're doing right
now we've paused our program and we're
taking a look at its state we're reading
its memory if I hit F10 again we're
going to advance this is now set to 9
it's set to 9 here as well pretty cool
stuff you can see that string is still
uninitialized stch memory but check this
out I'm about to initialize it aren't I
so if I hit F10 it's initialized because
this is an actual pointer it's also
telling us the memory address of that
string so if I was to copy this memory
address here from the watch window and
paste it into my memory View and hit
enter look at this I'm taking to these
bytes which in this ask interpretation
you can see that it says hello and
what's really interesting is that if you
actually keep reading you can see that
our program literally contains memory
close to this hello variable that says
stack around the variable was corrupted
the variable is being used without being
initialized obviously our program
containing string like stack around the
variable was corrupted in its memory is
not something that will exist in release
mode but it's just another great example
of what will actually happen in debug
mode to help you debug your program Okay
cool so things are getting really
interesting here because we've run into
this for Loop what's going to happen if
I keep advancing through this now we
haven't covered for Loops or any kind of
control flow statements in this series
yet the next few videos are probably
going to deal with it I really wanted to
cover the debugger first so that we can
actually step through these control flow
statements in the future and see how
they work and you guys already know how
to use this debug view but basically f
is going to do stuff multiple times so
if we step through this program you can
see that I set to zero it's going to
grab index Zero from this string which
is going to be the very first character
in the string which is a capital H if we
hit F10 we can hover our Mouse over C
and see that it's set to H we can also
come over here into watch and just type
in C and you can see we're now taking a
look at what C is when I hit F10 it's
going to log that letter to the console
and then when it gets back to this curly
bracket it's going to run this
comparison it's going to compare is I
less than five and then if so it's going
to increment I and then jump back into
here so if I hit F10 you can see we jump
up here to do the comparison if I hit
F10 again we've done the i++ I is now
one we're going to do the same thing all
over again except this time I is one so
it's going to grab the second character
which is the letter e and continue on in
this case see is equal to e you can see
that it's changed here in our watch if
we come up here do Ampersand C and hit
enter you can see we have 65 which is
the letter e according to our ask view
fantastic I can keep running through
this and everything's going to be great
now suppose that I wanted to exit this
for Loop and maybe jump to this log
function I don't really care about
stepping through this I get how it works
how do I get out of this for Loop if I
try and step out or hit shift f11 it's
actually going to exit the whole
function I don't want to do that that I
just want to kind of keep running the
full loop and then stop here how do I do
that well it's pretty simple all you
have to do is put a breako on where you
want to stop next and if I hit F5 or
press the continue button up here it's
actually going to run my program until
it hits the next breakpoint which in
this case is this log function so by
this point you can see that the memory
that used to make up this C variable is
set to O it's actually still active that
memory is still there even though we've
gone out of scope and we'll talk about
that in the future but the memory is set
to the very last character of the word
hello and if we bring back our program
you can see it's printed up that entire
hello word and then we're about to
execute this hello world log if I hit
F10 we're going to jump to the next line
of code here it's going to print hello
world now we've actually paused
execution of this program because we had
a break point here and I just hit F10 so
if I press enter here nothing's actually
going to happen I need to hit F5 and
then our program will close because it
is going to still detect that enter
press so that's it a fantastically
simple overview of basic debugging
there's going to be a lot more to this
but what I just showed in this video is
going to be the basis of how we actually
debug our code remember a program is
really just made up of memory even the
instruction pointer which is where in
our program we actually are executing
code and the actual code that we're
executing all of that is stored in
memory so being able to view our memory
is really all we have and really all we
need and by setting break points it lets
us pause our program at a give time at a
given line of code and actually inspect
it and take a look to see what all of
our variables are set to which of course
is going to be incredibly useful when
you're running code hope you guys
enjoyed this video if you did please hit
that like button let's see if we can
beat our like record I don't know I
think it's about 800 so let's just let's
just let's just smash that you can
follow me on Twitter and Instagram I've
been posting some pretty cool photos on
Instagram lately so you're just you
you're just not going to want to miss
that at all and if you really like this
series you can support me on patreon.com
Theo now the cool thing about this is by
doing so you'll get access to early
drafts of videos and the cool thing
about those early drafts is not
everything in the draft makes it to the
final video to this so you get to see
stuff that might be cut from the final
video exclusive and as well as that of
course you are supporting this series
and you're enabling me to make more of
these videos more often which is pretty
awesome awesome hope you guys have a
great day and I'll see you in the next
video
[Music]
goodbye